apart of branches git has another type of links to commits, the so-called tags.
Its easy to create one: "git tag tagname", for example like that
and commit to which tag should point, its "HEAD" by default, lets use this one.
I can use tag, instead of commit identifier after its created, e.g. "git show --quiet tagname" like that.
also as tag is a link to commit you can see it in the "git log" output
the difference between the branch and tag is that tag is just a label and its not going to move anywhere and always pointing to the same commit.
so if we make a commit, while being in a branch, the corresponding link will move, as we saw it earlier.
Tag is way more simple, once created it always points to the commit, so its just a label with no complex mechanics behind the scenes.
The most often usage is
release labling
for example, we want to point that with this commit we released this version
Also, its very convenient and important, that tag, unlike the branch, is not moving anywhere with commits made.
The point that this commit is associated with some version released is final and we note exactly this fact.
Later on we can get back to it, if we want to and create a separate branch for the changes of 1.x version
that is initially going to point to the same commit as tag does and
continue the development there. But in any case, nothing can change the fact that this commit has release 1.0.0 and
future releases are going to have their tags.
use the "git tag" command to see a list of tags.
There are additional parameters, filters, e.g. I want to see which releases are having the commit Im interested in, this one.
This release only.
Also one can add the "-n" flag to print
the commit message to which tag is pointing and the number of lines of this message, that should be printed( one line by default ),
most if the time its enough.
And here are our tags with messages
further if Im interested in details I can check it using "git show" or "git log",
print the history of development, starting with the current tag and so on.
If you have plenty of tags output can be limited. E.g. project has many versions and Im only interested in the ones that are starting with
"1.1". For that I add "-l" and the corresponding mask. For now I only have one such version, I may have more later.
More filters can be found in the documentation.
Tags can be of two kinds: first - the ones called lightweight tags,
that are links to commits.
second - tags with annotation. Previously we used the lightweight tags only, let me remove them now.
for that "-d" and further the name of the tags, that I want to remove.
Done. To create an annotated tag "-a" flag is used and the rest is the same.
If we run it now, editor will open in which we should write the description of the tag or we can use the "-m" flag
exactly as we do for commit, right in the command line.
I will create one more tag, let it point exactly where master branch is pointing now.
The main difference between the annotated tag is that it has the information, so its not a bare label, but a label with
the message. As we saw above also storing the information on who and made it and when it was made.
So in our case the one who decided to release this exact commit, which might be quite important.
To demonstrate it
Im going to call "git show" with our new, annotated tag and
you see, unlike the lightweight tag we have an information of who have created this tag, when was it created, who created it and
of course, the description and then the commit as annotated tags are more
informative in most cases it is recommended to use it.